Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is בבא מציעא י"ח,
Bava Metzia yud chet, 18. We pick up two lines from the
top of י"ח עמוד א', yud chet amud alef, and our learning
should be in memory of my nephew מעוז Ma'oz Morel, זכר צדיק
לברכה, zecher tzaddik livracha, and in prayer for the safety and security
of our troops and the swift return of the hostages. Okay, we
pick up from two lines from the top and we're in the
middle of a discussion of trying to prove whether a woman who
becomes an אלמנה, almanah, becomes a widow from אירוסין, erusin, whether she
collects her כתובה. kesuvah. And this is part of a larger discussion
of whether somebody can say פרעתי parati after מעשה בית דין, ma'aseh
beis din, which we'll get back to in a minute. But let's
first take, or say לא היו דברים מעולם. lo hayu devarim me'olam.
But let's take a look here first with this question about whether
an אלמנה almanah from אירוסין, erusin, a woman who had קידושין kiddushin
and did not yet have נישואין, nisuin, and then the husband died,
whether she would collect her כתובה. kesuvah. Okay, so it says like
this, ואלא מדתני רבי חייא בר אמי. ve-ela mi-detani Rebbi Chiya bar
Ami. So we can prove it from what רבי חייא בר אמי
Rebbi Chiya bar Ami teaches. אשתו ארוסה לא אונן ולא מיטמא לה.
ishto arusah lo onen velo mitameh lah. If a man has קידושין
kiddushin but not נישואין, nisuin, so his wife is considered an ארוסה,
arusah, not a נשואה, nisuah, gave the ring but did not have
the חופה chuppah or started living together in the home, so that's
the status of ארוסה, arusah, and then she dies, so he does
not become an אונן, onen, the laws of mourning do not
apply, and whether that means not doing מצוות mitzvot or relating to
קרבנות korbanot if he's a כהן. kohen. ולא מיטמא לה, velo mitameh
lah, and also if he's a כהן kohen he does not become
טמא tamei to her because there's no מצוה mitzvah of becoming טמא
tamei or of burial to a wife who is only an ארוסה
arusah and not yet a נשואה. nisuah. That's because it's learned out
from כי אם לשארו הקרוב אליו, ki im lish'ero hakarov eilav, his
flesh that is close to him, and they're not considered to be
like בשר אחד basar echad until they start living together. Okay, וכן
היא, ve-chein hi, and similarly if he were to die, then היא
לא אוננת ולא מיטמא לו. hi lo onenet velo mitama lo. She
doesn't become an אוננת onenet and she also doesn't become טמאה temeah
to him. Now, of course, she does not have the prohibitions of
טומאה, tumah, only a male כהן kohen has those prohibitions, but it
basically means that she has no obligations of burial. Okay,
מתה אינו יורשה. meisah eino yorshah. If she dies, he does not
inherit her. Again, all of the sort of reciprocal rights and responsibilities
only kick in from נישואין. nisuin. His obligation to support her, to
house her, the fact that when she dies he will inherit her,
that only begins from נישואין. nisuin. So if she dies, he doesn't
inherit her. מת הוא גובה כתובתה. meis hu gova kesuvatah. If he
dies, she can still collect her כתובה. kesuvah. So there you see,
it's explicit. A woman from אירוסין erusin has a right to a
כתובה. kesuvah. So the גמרא Gemara says maybe not, דילמא דכתב לה.
dilma de-kasav lah. Maybe it's talking about a case where he explicitly
wrote the כתובה kesuvah from the time of אירוסין, erusin, but without
that she does not have the rights to the כתובה kesuvah until
נישואין. nisuin. וכי תימא דכתב לה מאי למימרא. ve-chi teima de-kasav lah
mai lemimra. If you'll say well okay, then what's the חידוש? chiddush?
Why did it have to say you collect the כתובה kesuvah if
it was explicitly written? It's obvious. No, מתה אינו יורשה אצטריכא ליה.
meisah eino yorshah itztricha leih. You had to tell me because of
the הלכה halacha that if she dies he does not inherit her.
And therefore, so
that you might not have known that, and since it was teaching
you the הלכה halacha of מתה אינו יורשה, meisah eino yorshah, right,
and that also relates to the issue of נישואין, nisuin, it also
taught you the sort of flip that while that's true she does
collect her כתובה. kesuvah. But actually, we're talking about the fact that
the כתובה kesuvah was explicitly written. Okay, so you can't prove from
there that without a כתובה kesuvah being written that a woman has
a right to collect it from the אירוסין. erusin. And it was
because we had assumed that, אביי Abaye had assumed that a woman
collects it from the אירוסין erusin that he retracted the way he
was trying to deal with an evidence that was brought earlier. What
was the evidence that was brought earlier? That this principle, this idea
that הטוען אחר מעשה בית דין לא אמר כלום, ha-to'en achar ma'aseh
beis din lo amar klum, that something that is sort of, you
know, an obligation from the court, something that the חז"ל Chazal impose
on someone, so for example, the payment of a כתובה kesuvah even
if a כתובה kesuvah is not written, it's the husband's obligation to
the wife, then therefore you're not believed to say that you paid
it up. That was the statement of רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. Okay,
so and the proof of it that was given was this הלכה
halacha that if a woman takes out her גט get without a
כתובה, kesuvah, then she can still collect it, collect her כתובה. kesuvah.
And the husband is not believed to say that he paid the
כתובה. kesuvah. So there you go. Why is that? She doesn't have
her כתובה. kesuvah. Why should she be able to collect? Why should
he not be believed? So Must be because the obligations of כתובה
ksuva are מעשה בית דין, maaseh beis din, and therefore that's why
he's not believed. That was the evidence that was brought to show
that if somebody claims they've paid up some standing obligation of the
court, they're not believed unless they bring evidence. All right, that was
the proof. אביי Abaye said, well, maybe not, maybe it's talking only
about a case where they
normally don't write a כתובה, ksuva, and then that got into the
whole discussion about comparing that to a case of an ארוסה arusa
and so on. All right, but that was the case we were
dealing with. Now we have said
אביי Abaye did not reject it for the reason we were thinking
about yesterday, the difference between a place you write כתובה ksuva and
you don't write כתובה ksuva because of this whole issue about ארוסה.
arusa. So why did אביי Abaye reject it? For the following reason.
Okay? So it says אלא אביי מגופא דמתניתין קהדר ביה. ela Abaye
migufei demasnisin kahadar bei. It was from the very משנה Mishnah itself
that he realized that he couldn't make a claim that that משנה
Mishnah was
talking only about a place that אין כותבין כתובה. ein kosvin ksuva.
Why? מגופא דמתניתין קהדר ביה migufei demasnisin kahadar bei
because what did אביי Abaye say? אביי Abaye said maybe the idea
that the גט get works is not because of מעשה maaseh without
a כתובה ksuva is not because of מעשה בית דין, maaseh beis
din, maybe the reason that the גט get works is because if
it's a place that you don't normally write כתובה, ksuva, the גט
get effectively functions as a כתובה. ksuva. So the reason is not
because of מעשה בית דין maaseh beis din that the husband isn't
believed, it's because the גט get is functioning as a כתובה, ksuva,
and you're not believed to say you paid up a debt when
somebody is holding a שטר. shtar. So in this case, the woman's
שטר shtar is not the כתובה, ksuva, the woman's שטר shtar is
the גט get because in a place where they don't write כתובה,
ksuva, the גט get becomes effectively like a כתובה. ksuva. Okay, so
that's what אביי Abaye said, you can't bring a proof from that.
And that led to this whole discussion about whether an ארוסה arusa
has a כתובה. ksuva. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to
say no, no, forget that point, here's why אביי Abaye said that
you cannot say that was the case of the משנה Mishnah and
push away the evidence from that משנה. Mishnah. Why? He says like
this, די סלקא דעתך במקום שאין כותבין כתובה עסקינן, de i salka
daatach bimakom she’ein kosvin ksuva askinan, if it was like אביי Abaye
tried to say to push off this evidence and say no, no,
no, that's not because of מעשה בית דין, maaseh beis din, the
reason there the husband isn't believed is because the גט get functions
like a written כתובה, ksuva, because it's a place that they don't
write כתובה. ksuva. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, let's see if
that really makes sense that we can treat the גט get like
a כתובה ksuva without introducing this idea of מעשה בית דין. maaseh
beis din. So let's take a look. קהדר ביה די סלקא דעתך
במקום שאין כותבין כתובה עסקינן, kahadar bei de i salka daatach bimakom
she’ein kosvin ksuva askinan,
if this case of the woman collecting based on the גט get
was a place where כתובה ksuva is not normally written, דגיטא היינו
כתובתה, deget hainu ksuvasan, and the reason is not because of מעשה
בית דין maaseh beis din but because in such a place the
גט get is seen as a כתובה. ksuva. So the גמרא Gemara
is going to say, is that really possible without introducing this idea
of מעשה בית דין? maaseh beis din? So let's take a look.
אטו גט מנה מאתים כתיב ביה? atu get maneh masayim kesiv bei?
How could the גט get function as a כתובה? ksuva? The גט
get doesn't say the amount, doesn't say whether the husband agreed to
100 or 200, and maybe he added a תוספת. tosefes. So the
גט get by itself, even though it proves she's divorced, obviously is
not evidence to the debt, the only, or to the amount, the
specifics of the debt. The only way you know the specifics is
by introducing the fact that there is a בית דין beis din
obligation for כתובה ksuva that we assume is present. All right? וכי
תימא כיון דתקנו רבנן למגבא ליה כמאן דכתב לה דמי. vechi teima
keivan detakinu rabanan lemigba lei keman dechasav lah dami. So now you'll
say, okay, but wait a minute, it's still not the מעשה בית
דין maaseh beis din itself which is the evidence against the man,
it's still the גט, get, but in a society in which,
in a location in which they don't write a כתובה, ksuva, and
there's known that there's a standard obligation of either 200 or 100
based on the woman's status, in that type of a place, we
see the גט get as if it is testifying to the obligation
of 100 or 200. So it's not the מעשה בית דין maaseh
beis din itself that he's not believed to
say פרעתי, parati, it's because of the שטר, shtar, the גט get
is the שטר shtar that is as if it is testifying to
his obligation of 100 or 200, and if you have a שטר,
shtar, you're not believed to say פרעתי, parati, but it's still because
of the שטר, shtar, not just because of the מעשה בית דין.
maaseh beis din. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say, is
that really going to work? Let's take a look.
So he
says וליתימא ליה פרעתי, veleisima lei parati, let him
no, he should be able to say פרעתי parati that he paid
up even if the גט get is serving as a שטר. shtar.
Why? וכי תימא דאמרינן ליה אי פרעת איבעי לך למיקרעיה, vechi teima
deamrinan lei i parat ivai lach lemikrei,
so we'll say, like, why isn't a person normally believed to say
that he paid up? Because if against a שטר shtar that the
מלוה malve is holding on,
because if you paid up, why is he holding on to the
שטר? shtar? So still we'll treat the גט get as the שטר
shtar and you're not believed like normally you're not believed. גמרא Gemara
says no, that. won't work here. Here even if we treat the
גט get as a שטר shtar he should be believed to say
פרעתי. parati. Why?
Because we would say to him, wow if you paid it up
why didn't you, why wasn't, why didn't you tear up the גט?
get? אמר לן, Amar lan, he would say back to us, לא
שבקת לי, lo shavkas li, you know, you wouldn't allow me. אמר
רבינא, Amar Ravina, you know, or she wouldn't want it, אמר רבינא
לינסובי ביה, Amar Ravina linsuvei beih, I need the גט get to
be not torn, I want to use it to prove that I
got divorced and to remarry and people are going to want to
see a full גט, get, if it's torn they'll question its validity.
Okay, so the גמרא Gmara says וכי תימא אמרינן ליה בעי לך
למיקרעיה, vechi teima amrinan leih bei lach lemikreiah, no,
no, no, if you paid up then even if she wouldn't agree
to write a גט get to tear the גט, get, you still,
you could have said listen let's do this, let's tear the גט
get ומכתב אגביה umichtav agabeih and have the בית דין beit din
write on the back of the גט, get, כתיבת דנא דקרענוהו, ketivat
dena dekarnuhu,
this גט get that we tore, לאו משום דגיטא פסולה הוא, lav
mishum degita psula hu, is not, do not infer from this that
this is an invalid גט, get, אלא כי היכי דלא תיגבי ביה
זימנא אחריתי, ela ki heichi delo tigbi beih zimna achriti, but that
she should not use it to collect her כתובה ksuva second time.
So you still we're not going to believe you to say פרעתי
parati for, because, you know, because you should have torn it up
like we would normally say to somebody who says פרעתי, parati, and
oh, you'll say well I can't tear it up because, you know,
she needs the גט, get, we'll say back to you why not
tear it up and have a בית דין beit din sign on
the back that, you know, that the גט get is כשר? kosher?
So the גמרא Gmara says אטו כל דמיגבי בבי דינא מיגבי, atu
kol demigbi bevei dina migbi, I don't, anybody who's paying up a
debt is paying it up in בית דין? beit din? Like what
do you mean? She doesn't have to go to בית דין, beit
din, she comes to the man, says give me my כתובה, ksuva,
he gives her the $200, they're not in front of the, the
200 זוז, zuz, they're not in front of a בית דין, beit
din, okay, and what's he able to do? He can't go ahead
and tear it, she won't let him, don't, you can't say tear
it and have a בית דין beit din sign on the back,
the בית דין beit din isn't around. So there's a reasonable explanation
how he could have paid and she could still be holding on
to the גט. get. So what the גמרא Gmara is saying is
the following: this case is evidence that you cannot say פרעתי parati
in a case of מעשה בית דין, maaseh beit din, an obligation
of the court. Because you want to say that no, this is
not because of just the abstract obligation of the court, the גט
get is the שטר shtar and that's why he's not believed to
say פרעתי. parati. That's not true. If it were just because of
the גט, get, there's, he would be believed to say פרעתי parati
because there's a reason she could still be holding the גט get
even after he paid up, which isn't true by other שטרות. shtarot.
So if despite that he's not believed to say פרעתי, parati, it's
not because of the power of her holding the שטר, shtar, that
is not so meaningful in this case because there could be a
reason that she's still holding on to it, and rather it is
because of the מעשה בית דין. maaseh beit din. So in the
end this is evidence to רב יוחנן's Rav Yochanan position that if
somebody claims that they paid up a גט get standing obligation, you
know, that the court has imposed, then that person is not believed
unless they're able to bring evidence to that. And that's the end
of that discussion. I should also say about the issue about whether
an ארוסה arusa gets a כתובה, ksuva, even though the גמרא Gmara
says you can't prove it from these cases that we were talking
about, maybe they were special cases that he explicitly wrote כתובה, ksuva,
והלכה ve-halacha nevertheless is that an ארוסה arusa does get a base
כתובה. ksuva. She doesn't get תוספת tosefet without it being written, but
she does get a base כתובה. ksuva. Okay, now we can go
on to the next משנה. mishna. Still about finding things and returning
them, but finding, you know, interesting things. This פרק perek is about
like interesting things that happen when something is found. We'll get to
the next פרק perek where we'll deal with the basic obligation to
return a lost object. Okay. מוצא גיטי נשים ושחרורי עבדים, motzei gittei
nashim veshichrurei avadim, so now you, somebody finds, you know, a גט,
get, you know, it says ראובן Reuven divorces his wife שרה, Sarah,
or a writ of manumission of freeing a slave, דייתיקי, diatiki, a
דייתיקי diatiki which is a statement that somebody, you know, somebody who
was on his deathbed gave away, you know, dispersed his property, so
it's a testimony to what he said, like a will. מתנה, matana,
or a שטר shtar that gifts a plot of land to somebody.
ושובר, veshover, or a שובר shover which is a receipt, you know,
you paid the, you paid the debt, and the creditor did not
have the שטר shtar to give back to you but he wrote
you out a receipt that you've paid the debt. Okay, you found
all those things. הרי זה לא יחזיר, harei zeh lo yachzir, do
not give it back to the, you know, person who is,
you know, we're assuming that it's that person's, don't give the person
to whom it was intended. Don't give it to the woman, right,
don't give it to the slave, don't give it to the receiver
of the gift, don't give it to the person for whom the
receipt was written. Don't give it to the intended parties, right, and
assume that it fell from them. Why? שאני אומר כתובין היו, she-ani
omer ketuvin hayu, maybe they were written by the husband, by the
owner of the slave, by the creditor, all these things were written
by the, you know, ונמלך עליהן שלא ליתנן, venimlach aleihen she-lo letnan,
and in the end they weren't given, they changed their mind, decided
not to give it. Okay, so even though So you have found
these things, you don't know whether they fell from the person who
wrote them or from the receiving party, a party for whom they
were intended. And don't even say, "Well, since they were intended for
that person, I might as well deliver it to that party because
it was intended to that party." No, maybe the person who wrote
it changed their mind. So therefore, you have to just hold on
to it until more evidence is brought. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says.
טעמא, Ta'ama, says the גמרא, Gemara, the reason דנמלך שלא ליתנם, denimlach
shelo litnam, the concern is that they changed their mind, the person
who wrote them. הא אמר תנו נותנין, Ha amar tenu nosnin, but
if the person would say, "Go ahead and give it," you know,
the husband would say, "Yes, you know, I did give that גט
get to my wife," or says, "It fell from me and I
still want you to go ahead," you know, "I hadn't given it
yet but I'm okay with you going ahead and giving it," the
implication in the משנה Mishnah would be that you would give it.
Right, the only concern is that they changed their mind. If you
knew they hadn't changed their mind, then you could deliver it to
the intended party. ואפילו לזמן מרובה, Va'afilu l'zman merubeh, even presumably if
you found this a while after it was lost. Okay, so somebody
basically says, you know, "I dropped my גט," get, or the שליח
shaliach was bringing the גט get and he says, "I dropped it,"
and nobody could find it and then a few days later you
found it and the husband says, "Yeah, I want the גט get
to go to my wife, I still want it to go to
my wife," the implication is then everybody should be happy and you
can go ahead and give it. But the גמרא Gemara says, "Wait
one minute, there's a problem here, not a problem like maybe he
didn't divorce her yet or whatever," because again, he's saying "give it,"
so even, you know, it doesn't matter if she had already received
it, she hadn't received it yet, he's saying "give it," you'll give
it now. But if it took a while between the time it
was lost and the time it was found, how do you know
that we're dealing with the same גט? get? All right, so the
גמרא Gemara says ורמינהו, u-raminhu, I'll ask you on this. המביא גט,
Hameivi get, if a שליח shaliach is bringing a גט get ואבד
הימנו v'avad heimenu and he lost it, מצאו לאלתר, mats'o l'altar, if
immediately he starts looking around and like right then and there he's
able to find it, fine, כשר, kasher, it's good because you say
he found the same גט get that he lost.
אם לאו פסול, Im lav pasul, but if he only found it
out, you know, a few days later,
it's invalid. Why?
Because maybe it was a different גט. get. So how come our
משנה Mishnah implies that the only concern is that the husband changed
his mind and if we know that the husband still wants to
divorce his wife or you know that we would go ahead and
give it? Why is that? Maybe it's not the same גט. get.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava,
לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן במקום ששיירות מצויות כאן
במקום שאין שיירות מצויות. Kan b'makom sheshayarot metsuyot, kan b'makom she-eina shayarot
metsuyot. It depends, you know, what's the likelihood that you would have
a גט get with the exact same names, you know, in this
location where it was lost. You know, what are the chances? So
the only time we would be concerned that it wasn't the same
גט get would be, but happened to be another person's גט get
with exactly the same names, would be in a place where there's
a lot of travel, השיירות מצויות, hashayarot metsuyot,
the caravans are very common. You found it in the middle of
Times Square, you found it in a busy thoroughfare where lots of
people are always traveling from different places. In that type of a
case we could be concerned that maybe it was somebody else's גט
get that happened to have the same names. Okay, and that's in
that case is when the משנה Mishnah says don't, you know, if
you found it only after, if the שליח shaliach found it only
after a while, he has to be concerned it might not be
the same גט. get. But in our משנה Mishnah where the only
concern is that the husband might have changed his mind, but otherwise
you would give it if you found it later, if you know
if he says, "I still do want to divorce my wife," that's
in a case where it's not a busy thoroughfare and you could
be confident that it's the same גט. get. Okay.
כאן במקום ששיירות מצויות. Kan b'makom sheshayarot metsuyot. And now the גמרא
Gemara says and not only that, we're going to, we're going to
limit it even more, how, what are the circumstances you have to
worry that, that it might be a different גט, get, because it
is a little bizarre, right? So the גמרא Gemara is going to
say not only are we saying it has to be a busy
thoroughfare, there's another criterion as well. ואפילו במקום ששיירות מצויות, Va'afilu b'makom
sheshayarot metsuyot,
even in a place where there are a lot of caravans, והוא
שהוחזקו שני יוסף בן שמעון בעיר אחת. vehu shehuchzeku shnei Yosef ben
Shimon b'ir achat. Even then it would only be if you knew
that there were two people in this city with the same names.
Because remember, a גט get says also what the city, what city
it was, it was in. So if the גט get says, you
know, in Manhattan, יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon divorced his wife
שרה בת רחל. Sarah bas Rachel. Okay, and now you the שליח
shaliach was bringing the גט, get, you know, and it said יוסף
בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon of Manhattan is divorcing his wife שרה
בת רחל. Sarah bas Rachel. He loses it and he finds another
one that has exactly the same names. So we're saying you do
not have to be concerned it's, it's somebody else's גט get unless
two things. Number one is it's a busy thoroughfare and number two,
you know that in Manhattan there are two people whose names are
יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon who have wives names of שרה
בת רחל. Sarah bas Rachel. But and if you so if you
know that that possibility concretely exists, that there's another couple with those
names in the same location and it's a busy thoroughfare, then you
have to be concerned. So it is an extreme limiting of this
משנה Mishna that if you lose a גט Gett and you find
it, don't find it more than a while after, you can't use
it. It extremely narrows the application of that to a cases where
busy thoroughfare and you know that there are people with exact same
names and therefore there is something to be worried about. Okay, so
and אילו תימא הכי, ilo tema hachi, if you don't say this,
you don't say there are two criteria, you say there's only one
criterion and a busy thoroughfare is enough to worry that it might
not be the same גט. Gett. תא שמע דרבא אדרבא, Ta shma
de-Raba ad-Raba, we would have a contradiction with two statements of רבא.
Raba. רבא Raba here said it's based on a busy thoroughfare. But
here's another statement: דההוא גיטא דאשתכח בבי דינא דרב הונא. De-hahu gitta
de-ishtakach be-bei dina de-Rav Huna. There was a גט Gett that was
found in the בית דין beis din of רב הונא, Rav Huna,
and the גמרא Gemara is going to say that a בית דין
beis din is like a place where there are a lot of
caravans,
people are always moving in and out of the בית דין. beis
din. So there was a גט Gett that was found there דהוה
כתיב ביה בשוירי מתא דעל רכיס נהרא De-hava ksiv bei be-Shviri masa
d-al Rechis nahara in this city שוירי מתא, Shviri masa, which is
on the river
רכיס נהרא, Rechis nahara, and that was the location. It said ראובן
Reuven is divorcing his wife שרה. Sarah. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav
Huna, so רב הונא Rav Huna said, and then the שליח shliach
said, "Oh yeah, that's the גט Gett that I lost." So רב
הונא Rav Huna said, חיישינן לשני שוירי, Chashinan le-shnei Shviri, that actually
we would not, we don't return it to the שליח. shliach. Maybe
there's another city called שוירי Shviri also on the same river, also
with people with the same names that a husband is divorcing his
wife. Okay, so here he was concerned with that and you could
say okay that's a case of שיירות מצויות, shayaroos metzuyos, there are
caravans, so now why didn't he say we're concerned that in that
city there are two people with the same name? So רש"י Rashi
says we knew that in the city of the שליח shliach there
weren't two people with the same name with those wives of the
same name, and רב הונא Rav Huna was still concerned, maybe there's
another city, same name city, same name husband, same name wives. So
he was concerned. שיירות מצויות Shayaroos metzuyos is enough of a reason,
busy thoroughfare for us to be concerned that it might be a
different גט. Gett. But we're not done, because the question is רבא's
Raba position. ואמר ליה רב חסדא לרבא, V-amar lei Rav Chisda le-Raba,
so רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to רבא, Raba, פוק עיין בה
דלאורתא בעי מינך רב הונא. Puk ayen bah d-le-orsa ba'ei minach Rav
Huna. Go research this, it's like the judges have their clerks. Go
and research this because רב הונא Rav Huna is just hesitating to
return it, he's concerned maybe it might be a different גט, Gett,
and go and research it because רב הונא Rav Huna will ask
you in the evening what the הלכה halacha is, your advice about
whether it should be returned or shouldn't be returned. נפק דק ואשכח,
Nafak dak v-ashkach,
so רבא Raba went out and he found the following. Now we
teach in a משנה, Mishna, and this is right here from our
פרק, Perek, כל מעשה בית דין הרי זה יחזיר. Kol ma'aseh beis
din harei zeh yachzir. Anything that is coming from the courts, meaning
like the court has validated the signatures let's say of a שטר
חוב, shtar chov, of a document of a debt, so then you
give it back to the מלווה malveh because if the signatures were
validated it meant that the מלווה malveh had a process in the
court and therefore the לוה loveh isn't believed or whatever and you
give it back to the מלווה. malveh. That's what the משנה Mishna
says. Okay, but now besides the question of was it paid up
or not paid up, what about the question of are they the
right people? והאי בי דינא דרב הונא דכי
מקום שיירות מצויות דמי. V-hai bei dina de-Rav Huna de-chi makom shayaroos
metzuyos dami. So it says what was רבא's Raba evidence from this?
So you see if you give it back to the מלווה malveh
in the case of a מעשה בית דין, ma'aseh beis din, so
presumably it's a מעשה בית דין ma'aseh beis din and it was
found in the courthouse. That's what רבא's Raba assuming. And he says
look, we have evidence that you're not concerned that it might be
somebody else because it says מעשה בית דין ma'aseh beis din you
return it. So therefore רבא Raba said to רב הונא, Rav Huna,
you know what, you actually are allowed to return it. You're not
concerned that it might be somebody else from this משנה Mishna that
teaches a מעשה בית דין ma'aseh beis din you return to the
מלווה malveh or to the person who wrote the שטר shtar or
to whose benefit the שטר shtar is. הרי זה יחזיר. Harei zeh
yachzir. So now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so that sounds like
רבא, Raba, you do return a שטר shtar even in a place
where it's a busy thoroughfare. והאי בי דינא דרב הונא דכי מקום
שיירות מצויות דמי. V-hai bei dina de-Rav Huna de-chi makom shayaroos metzuyos
dami. The בית דין beis din of רב הונא Rav Huna is
a place where it's like a busy thoroughfare. וקפשיט רבא דיחזיר. U-k-pashit
Raba d-yachzir.
And רבא Raba learned from this principle that מעשה בית דין ma'aseh
beis din that if a בית דין beis din has validated the
signatures, that you return the
document and you're not concerned that it might have been from somebody
else with the same name. אלמא, Alma, so what's the explanation?
Is a busy thoroughfare enough to be concerned like רבא Raba said
or not? Here רבא Raba doesn't seem to be bothered by it.
אלמא, Alma, you see that it requires two things: אי הוחזקו שני
יוסף בן שמעון אין אלו לא. Ei huchzaku shnei Yosef ben Shimon
in ilo lo. That רבא Raba requires both that it be a
busy thoroughfare and that you know that there are people with the
same name in the same city. And if you don't have that,
both of those things happening, then you are not concerned. not concerned
that it just so by total chance happens exact same document with
the exact same names. Alright so that's what we've done we've severely
limited these cases of being concerned it might be a different document
with identical names to places which is a busy thoroughfare and where
we know that there are people with the same names in that
place. Okay. עבד רבא עובדא Avad Rava uvda בקיטנא דפומבדיתא. be'kitna de'Pumbedita.
So רבא Rava did a פסק pask this
הלכה halacha in the place of flax in פומבדיתא Pumbedita כשמעתיה k'shmatei
following his פסק psak meaning he said a גט get was lost
and then it was found a while after not immediately and he
said that's okay return it to the שליח. shaliach. And he was
not concerned that it might have been a different one. איכא דאמרי
Ika d'amri היכא דמזבני קיטנא. heicha de'mizveni kitna. Some say what does
it mean the place of flax? Some say it means the place
where flax is sold in the marketplace. Okay so that is a
place of a busy thoroughfare. So why did he have it returned?
והוא שלא הוחזקו Ve'hu she'lo huchzaku and but it was a place
but it was a case where you did not know that there
were also other people with the exact same names. אף על גב
דשכיחי שיירתא. Af al gav de'shchichi shayerata. So even though there were
caravans and it was a busy thoroughfare one version of the story
is he returned it because it was a busy place but we
didn't know that there were people with the same names and therefore
he's prepared to return it. ואיכא דאמרי Ve'ika d'amri another say היכא
דטרו קיטנא. heicha de'taru kitna. No no no it was found in
the place where they actually soak the
flax out in the industrial zone where there are very few people.
ואף על גב דהוחזקו Ve'af al gav de'huchzaku
and even though it actually was coming from a place where there
are a couple with the exact same name he was prepared to
return it why? דלא שכיחי שיירתא de'lo shchichi shayerata because caravans were
not common it was not a public thoroughfare. Okay so one more
time our משנה mishna says that you don't give a גט get
because you're afraid the husband changed his mind which sounds like if
the husband says give it you would give it and we're not
concerned that the גט get you found might be a different one.
We have another משנה mishna that is concerned that if you lost
a גט get and did not find it immediately it might be
a different one. And רבא Rava comes and extremely limits the case
when we would be concerned about that only in a case of
a busy thoroughfare and then the גמרא Gemara adds because of the
story of רב הונא Rav Huna and that you know for sure
that there's another couple with the exact same name in that town.
Okay that's רבא. Rava. רבי זירא רמי מתניתין אברייתא ומשני. Rabbi Zeira
rami matnitin a'braita u'meshani.
So רבא Rava showed these two משניות mishnayot seem to be contradicting
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira makes a similar question between a משנה mishna
and a ברייתא. braita. What's his question? תנן Tnan המביא גט
ואבד הימנו ha'meivi get ve'avad heimenu the משנה mishna that we quoted
that רבא Rava quoted and that was a משנה mishna in גיטין
Gittin that if somebody brings a גט get and it was lost
a שליח shaliach המביא גט ואבד הימנו מצאו לאלתר כשר ואם לאו
פסול. ha'meivi get ve'avad heimenu matza'o l'altar kasher ve'im lav pasul.
Only if the שליח shaliach finds it immediately otherwise you can't use
the גט get you're afraid it might be
a
different גט. get. ורמינהי U'reminhi רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says I'll ask
you on this: מצא גט אשה בשוק. matza get isha ba'shuk. Okay
we have a ברייתא braita in גיטין. Gittin. If somebody finds a
woman's גט get in the marketplace. בזמן שהבעל מודה יחזיר לאשה אין
הבעל מודה לא יחזיר לא לזה ולא לזה. be'zman she'ha'baal modeh yachzir
l'isha ein ha'baal modeh lo yachzir lo l'zeh ve'lo l'zeh.
If the husband admits yes I had given it to my wife
then you give it to the wife. If he says no I
haven't given it then you don't give it. קתני מיהת Katani mihat
בזמן שהבעל מודה יחזיר לאשה be'zman she'ha'baal modeh yachzir l'isha
but it says that you would give it to the wife if
the husband says I used it to divorce her. ואפילו לזמן מרובה
Ve'afilu l'zman merubeh and that would be even if it would be
after a significant amount of time. It sounds like that you would
always return it to the wife once the husband admits that he
had used it to divorce her. So why is that? Don't we
have this משנה mishna that teaches that you're afraid that it might
be somebody else's גט get a different גט get with people with
the same name? So it's a similar question. The משנה mishna says
don't return it we're afraid it might be a different person's גט
get with the same names and this ברייתא braita says if the
husband admits that it fell from the wife you return it. Why
is that? ומשני U'meshani and he answers just like רבא Rava did:
כאן במקום ששיירות מצויות כאן במקום שאין שיירות מצויות. kan be'makom she'shayarot
metzuyot kan be'makom she'ein shayarot metzuyot.
Now when is the case where you return it? You return it
when there are not caravans that are common and then you're not
concerned that it was a different גט. get. When does the משנה
mishna teach you don't return it and you are concerned it's a
different גט? get? In a place where the caravans are common just
like רבא Rava said. Now remember רבא Rava then added or the
גמרא Gemara added for רבא Rava another
criterion. So the גמרא Gemara is going to talk about that. איכא
דאמרי Ika d'amri some say that for רבי זירא: Rabbi Zeira: והוא
שהוחזקו דלא נהדר ve'hu she'huchzaku de'lo nehadar that רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
said there are only two criteria that are needed before to say
we don't return it: one that there are caravans and number two
that we know that there are people with the same names in
that town. Okay that you need both of those to not return
it. והיינו דרבא Ve'hainu de'Rava and it's exactly like we said רבא's
Rava position was only with those two together do you not return
it. איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri another say אף על גב Af al
gav
No,
for him even without knowing there are people with the same names,
as long as it's a place where there are these caravans, that
is sufficient to say don't return it. We're afraid who knows, maybe
there are somebody with the same name. Seems very far-fetched. Rava who
limits it so significantly seems to make a lot of sense, but
it's possible that for Rab Zera that Rab Zera would say once
there are caravans, we would return it as long as we would,
excuse me, we would not return it even without knowing there are
people with the same names. ופליגי דרבא U'pligi de'Rava and he would
argue on Rava. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בשלמא
רבא לא אמר כרבי זירא, Bishlama Rava lo amar ke'Rabbi Zera, we
understand that Rava did not say like Rab Zera meaning
there meaning why did the way they ask the questions differ? Rava
asked a question from the משנה Mishna in גיטין Gittin that said
you're afraid it's a different גט Get to our משנה Mishna which
implied you would return it. So we under and Rab Zera asked
from a ברייתא. Braisa. So we understand that Rava didn't do the
same type of question as Rab Zera. מתניתין אלימא ליה לאקשויי, Matnitin
alima leh l'akshuyei, he'd rather ask from משנהs Mishna that contradict one
another. They're more authoritative, they're presumably the same הלכה halachic position, so
he'd rather show the contradiction of two סתם משנה. Stam Mishna. אלא
רבי זירא מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבא? Ela Rabbi Zera mai ta'ama
lo amar ke'Rava? But Rab Zera, why did he frame his question
as the one משנה Mishna in גיטין Gittin against a ברייתא Braisa
in גיטין? Gittin? You know, maybe the ברייתא Braisa isn't authoritative, maybe
the ברייתא Braisa is a different opinion. Why didn't he show the
prompt that it also contradicts our משנה Mishna right here in בבא
מציעא? Bava Metzia?
אמר לך, Amar lach, Rab Zera would say back to you: מי
קתני האמר תנונו? Mi katni ha'amar tenunu? Because our משנה Mishna is
not so evidently against that teaching. Why? What was your that you
Rava said that the משנה Mishna sounds like, you know, don't give
the גט Get because you're afraid because, excuse me, the משנה Mishna
said don't give the גט Get back because maybe the husband changed
his mind. So you inferred from that that it seems to say
that if the husband says give, you would give it. האמר תנונו.
Ha'amar tenunu. So he says, ואפילו זמן מרובה, V'afilu zman meruba, and
you then said further, not only does it suggest that if the
husband were to say give you would give it, but that you
would give it even if it was found only after a long
time. How do you know that? How do you know that's what
our משנה Mishna is implying? דילמא האמר תנונו ולעולם כדקיימא לן לאלתר,
Dilma ha'amar tenunu u'le'olam k'dikayma lan l'altar,
maybe it's true, our משנה Mishna implies or says don't give it
back maybe he changed his mind, so it's true that it implies
that if he said give it back, you would listen to him
and you would give it back. But maybe only in a case
when it was found right away and therefore it's completely consistent with
the משנה Mishna in גיטין Gittin that says, you know, if it's
found right away give it back and if it's not you assume
it's a different גט. Get. So why is the ברייתא Braisa better?
Maybe the ברייתא Braisa is also only talking about if it's found
right away. This is the difference between something being implied and something
being stated explicitly. The ברייתא Braisa says explicitly that
if the husband says give it back, you give it back to
the wife. So if it only was true in cases of being
found right away, it would not have said a categorical statement. If
you're going to say give it back to the wife and it's
not true in all cases, you have to be explicit. So because
the ברייתא Braisa says give it back, it implies you always give
it back whether right away or whether after a long time and
that goes against seems to go against the other משנה. Mishna. Our
משנה Mishna that just implies that if he were to say give
it back, maybe yes you would give it back, but only with
other criteria as well, only if it was found right away. Okay,
so that's how they why they frame their questions differently. But at
the end they both say there has to be additional criteria to
say don't give it back. Now the גמרא Gemara goes like this.
למאן דאמר לרבי זירא במקום ששיירות מצויות ואף על גב דלא הוחזקו
שניים יוסף בן שמעון ופליגי דרבא, L'man de'amar l'Rabbi Zera bimkom she'shayarot
metzuyot v'af al gav d'lo uchzaku shnayim Yosef ben Shimon u'pligi de'Rava,
according to the approach that Rab Zera said his position don't give
it back once there are caravans and even if you don't know
that there are people with the same name and he's different than
Rava, he only has one criterion. Rava has two criteria. במאי קמיפלגי?
Bimai kamifligi?
What leads to their different opinions? Not what's the conceptual basis, obviously
there's a conceptual basis that Rava's only concerned when there's a really
good reason to be concerned which makes a lot of sense, and
Rab Zera has a lower threshold to be concerned. But what is
the textual reason that they came to different conclusions, that Rava would
have decided you need two criteria to not return it and Rab
Zera only one?
So it says like this. במאי קמיפלגי? Bimai kamifligi? רבא סבר קתני
Rava savar katni because Rava says we teach כל מעשה בית דין
הרי זה יחזיר. Kol ma'aseh Beis Din harei zeh yachzir. The משנה
Mishna remember in the whole story with רב הונא Rav Huna and
Rava had to go research it and Rava says it says if
something is found being processed by the court, a שטר חוב, Shtar
chov, you give it back and that implies look you're not concerned
that it's somebody else's, you give it back, that was his evidence.
דאישתכח בבית דין עסקינן, D'ishtakach be'Beis Din askinan, he assumes that since
it was processed by the court, the case in that משנה Mishna
is that the document was found in the courthouse. ובית דין כמקום
ששיירות מצויות, U'Beis Din k'makom she'shayarot metzuyot,
and the בית דין Beis Din is like a place, you know,
in the courthouse is where people are coming from all over, it's
a place like where caravans pass through. So if that says that
if something was processed by the court you give it back. back
and you're not concerned that it's a different, that it's a you
know, a different document with the same names and we're talking that
it was found in the courthouse, it shows you give it back
even in places where there are caravans. So when you don't give
it back, it must be that there's yet another criterion, that not
only are there caravans, it's also you know that there are people
with the same names. והוא שהוחזקו לא יחזיר, v'hu she-huchzeiku lo yachzir,
so it must be that the only case that you don't give
it back is when you know that there are people with the
same names. לא הוחזקו יחזיר, lo huchzeiku yachzir, but as long as
you don't know there are people with the same names, you can
give it back because that is the case of מעשה בית דין
maaseh beis din you give it back. ורבי זירא, v'Rabbi Zeira, what
would Rabbi Zeira say? Why would he not be convinced about that?
אמר לך, amar lach, he would tell you, מי קתני כל מעשה
בית דין שנמצאו בבית דין? mi kateni kol maaseh beis din she-nimtzu
b'veis din? Because the Mishnah doesn't say anything processed by the court
that's found in the courthouse you give back. כל מעשה בית דין
יחזיר קתני, kol maaseh beis din yachzir kateni, something that has been
processed by the court you give it back, that's all it says.
ולעולם דמשכח ליה בראי, u-l'olam d'mashkach lei b'ra'i, but we would be
talking that it would be found outside of בית דין. beis din.
Okay, so there's no evidence there that it's found in בית דין.
beis din. So that is completely irrelevant, does not bring any evidence
and it's not clear that it was found in a place where
שיירות מצויות shayaros metzuyos and therefore I will say that if we
have to limit the case to say be concerned and not return
it, it's enough that it's a place where there are caravans, you
don't also need to know that there are people with the same
name. So that's their debate, that's their positions. But basically they say
the case where it says don't return it there has to be
special circumstances, maybe one criterion, maybe two, but there has to be
special circumstances before you're worried about returning it. Now we're going to
see some positions going in the opposite direction. רבי ירמיה אמר, Rabbi
Yirmeya amar, Rabbi Yirmeya says, כגון דקאמרי עדי מעולם לא חתמנו אלא
אגט אחד שיצא בין שמעון, k'gon d'ka'amri edei me'olam lo chasamnu ella
a-get echad she-yatza bein Shimon, that no, the case where it says
you do return it, the implication of our Mishnah or the Braisa
that says when the husband says it's hers you return it, that's
only in, that's the special case. The rule is you never return
it. We're always afraid, even in no caravans, even you don't know
people with the same name, we're always afraid. The rule is don't
return it. When you do return it, it's a special case. What's
the case? That the witnesses say, the witnesses who are signed on
the גט, get, they say yes, there was only one get we've
ever signed with these people's names. So since they're saying that, there's
no concern that it fell from anybody else. A get with this
ראובן בן שמעון Reuven ben Shimon and that שרה בת רחל Sarah
bat Rachel and these names of עדים, eidim, only one such get
exists in the world, and therefore that's the special case that you
can return it. אי הכי מאי למימרא? ei hachi mai l'meimra? So
the Gemara says if that's true, what's the חידוש? chiddush? I mean
it's obvious you would return it. No, there's still another possibility. מהו
דתימא ליחוש שמא שנים שמותיהן כשמותיהן ועדים כעדים קמשמע לן. mahu d'teima
leichush shema shenayim shemoseihen k'shemoseihen v'eidim k'eidim ka-mashma lan. Who knows, maybe
there's another get out there that has you know, ראובן בן שמעון
Reuven ben Shimon divorcing שרה בת רחל Sarah bat Rachel and also
two different, a different Reuven ben Shimon, a different Sarah bat Rachel
and as far as the names of the eidim, also two other
eidim that happen to have exactly the same names as these eidim.
So that much we're not concerned about. Okay, so that obviously would
be crazy to be concerned about that. But Rabbi Yirmeya you have
to appreciate is going in the opposite direction. He is saying as
a rule we do not return it and the case we return
it has to be a very special case. Let's just read one
more. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, כגון דקאמר נקב יש בו
בצד אות פלונית, k'gon d'ka'amar nekev yesh bo b'tzad os plonis,
that the שליח shaliach who lost it says, gives a סימן siman
which we'll get to in the next פרק perek and he says,
you know, in the third line you know by this letter there's
a hole and you look in the third line by that letter
there's a hole, so you know that it was his get and
that's also the special case that you return it. ודווקא, v'davka, says
the גמרא, Gemara, בצד אות פלונית, b'tzad os plonis, only if he's
specific, by this particular letter. אבל נקב בעלמא, aval nekev b'alma, if
he just says there's a hole in it, לא, lo, you would
not give it back because you know that's not such evidence. There
are other gittin that have holes, it doesn't really prove that it's
his. Okay, and this is a difference between a סימן מובהק siman
muvhak and סימן שאינו מובהק, siman she-eino muvhak, which we'll see later.
Like a siman which is absolute identification and as opposed to a
siman which, you know, only a certain percentage of things will be
like that but it's not definite that that's yours. There are a
lot of other things that are like, you know, a lot of
other gittin also have holes in them, doesn't prove that it's yours.
Okay, so why would he require it to be a siman muvhak?
Because the Gemara says, רב אשי מספקא ליה סימנין דאורייתא או דרבנן,
Rav Ashi mesafeka lei simanin d'Oraisa o d'Rabanan,
because Rav Ashi isn't certain if a siman, meaning that's not muvhak,
if a pretty generic siman, it was a black coat, you know,
it was a London Fog. All right, so that excludes a lot
of other things, but it doesn't really prove a whole lot. But
still, you say you lost it and you gave a siman, so
there's a question in the Gemara is if a סימן אינו מובהק
siman eino muvhak is דאורייתא d'Oraisa or דרבנן. d'Rabanan. And if it's
only דרבנן, d'Rabanan, then you would know we could allow it by
a מציאה metziah where it's a question of... about ownership and money
and rabbis have a lot more latitude, but we would not trust
that by a גט get where it relates to the personal status
of the woman. Okay, so therefore, since he did not know whether
to treat a normal סימן siman as valid דאורייתא, d'oraita, he would
only return it when it was a סימן מובהק, siman muvhak, a
hole right next to this letter. So again, for רבא Rava and
רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, you need a special case to not return
it, a real reason to think it might be somebody else, might
be a different גט. get. And for רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeya and
רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, you need a special case to return it,
evidence that it really is your
גט get before you will return it. Okay, we will stop here.